A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Records, circa 1744-1956, undated
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Albemarle County (Va.) Records, circa 1744-1956, undated
The Library of Virginia
1042636-1180991
64 boxes--60 found at Library of Virginia and 4 (1042636, 1042642, 1043214, 1141496) found at State Records Center--Library of Virginia, Archives Annex
Albemarle County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court records from Albemarle County.
Historical Information
Albemarle County was named for William Anne Keppel, second earl of Albemarle and governor of the Virginia colony from 1737-1754. The county was formed from Goochland County in 1744, and part of Louisa County and certain islands in the Fluvanna River, now called the James, were added later.
All order books, except the first, and many loose papers, created between 1748 and 1781, were destroyed during the Revolutionary War by British general Banastre Tarleton's raid on Charlottesville in 1781.
Scope and Content
Albemarle County (Va.) Records, circa 1744-1956, undated, consist of the following records series: Court Records (subfield series include Judgments, Criminal Records, Clerks' Records, Court Finance, Jury Records, Personal Documentation, Dockets and Chancery Records), County Administrative Records (subfield series include Board of Supervisors Records, Overseer of the Poor Records, Sheriffs' Records and Treasurer's Records), Road and Bridge Records, Land Records, Business Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Organization Records, Town Adminstrative Records, School Records, Election Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Health and Medical Records and Military and Pension Records. Some boxes contain UNPROCESSED records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Albemarle County Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm" found on the Library of Virginia's web site.
Albemarle County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Accomack County Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available at Virginia Memory.
For more information and a listing of lost records localities see Lost Records research note.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Albemarle County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia-- Albemarle County.
Geographical Names:
Albemarle County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia-- Albemarle County.
Contents List
- Records, circa 1794-1933
  Court Records: UNPROCESSED Judgments, 1871-1876, Transcript - judgment suit - Albemarle Oil and Gas Co. vs. T.P. Peyton, 1924, UNPROCESSED Commonwealth Causes, 1908-1910; Road and Bridge Records, 1794, 1933; Land Records: Maps - blueprints, UNPROCESSED Deeds, 1870; Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships: Unidentified plumber's ledgers, 1895-1897, Unidentified bank checkbook, 1886, Correspondence - Toothill Manufacturing Co., 1897; Tax and Fiscal Records, 1897.
- Records, 1805-1910
  Court Records: Judgments, Commonwealth Causes, Criminal Records, Executions, etc., 1805-1910; Tax and Fiscal Records, 1905-1906; Fiduciary Records, 1906, 1908. No chancery. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, 1784-1932
  Miscellaneous Records: Estray books, 1748-1854; Court Records: Transcripts of following Judgment suits Ludeman versus Dutar, 1921, King Lumber Company versus Faulconer, 1921, Admx. of Bowers versus Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company, 1917; Meyers Manufacturing Company versus King Lumber Company, 1915; Dun versus Chaloner, 1920; Exhibit - Deed, Southern Railway Company to Central Trust Company of New Yory, 1894; Witness attendance book, 1863-1890; Fee and Civil Records, 1937; Business Records: Samuel Lewis Account Book, 1839-1855; Racket Store Bank Book, 1929-1932
- Records, 1790-1915
  Court Records: Judgments and Dockets, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Land Records, Wills. Chancery pulled.
- Records, 1880s
  Court Records: Judgments, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Land Records. Chancery pulled.
- Records, 1791-1946
  Fiduciary Records: Appointments of Trustees and Letters of Administration; Court Records: Reports of Commissioners and Name Changes; Bonds; Business Records: Partnership Papers; Marriage Records and Vital Statistics: Marriage Contracts.
- Records, 1790-1914
  Court Records: Judgments, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records. Chancery pulled.
- Records, circa 1815-1956
  Court Records: Judgments, Fiduciary Records, Organizational records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths. Chancery pulled.
- Records, 1862-1914
  Agreement Report of Division, DB 64, p. 67; Amendment to the Constitution of By laws of Building Association, 1868,; Appointment of Trustee under Deed of Trust, 1907; Assignment of Bankrupt's Effects, 1867-1888; Bankruptcies recorded in Deed Book; Bonds; Contracts; Deed of Release, Deed of Trust, 1899; Deeds, 1874,1877; Boundaries, 1912; Extract of DB 123, p.463 (1902); Judgment, Condemnation 1907; Renunciation, 1862; Survey Reports; Law Orders substituting of Trustee, 1907-1914. All pulled from Albemarle Deeds.
- Records, circa 1744-1886
  Court Records: Judgments, Road and Bridge Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths.
- Records, circa 1794-1812
  Court Records: Judgments, Miscellaneous Records, County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Town Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths.
- Records, circa 1782-1820
  Miscellaneous Records, Court Records: Judgments, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Tax and Fiscal Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1789-1848
  Land Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Fiduciary Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Court Records, Miscellaneous Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1800-1817
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records.
- Records, circa 1807-1815
  Court Records: Judgments and Bonds/Commissions/Oaths.
- Records, circa 1795-1846
  County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Miscellaneous Records, Fiduciary Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1804-1830
  County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Miscellaneous Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1806-1818
  Tax and Fiscal Records, Court Records, Fiduciary Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1810-1829
  County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records, County Administrative Records: Sheriff's Records, Tax and Fiscal Records.
- Records, circa 1798-1819
  Miscellaneous Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1808-1848
  Miscellaneous Records, Court Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1814-1853
  Tax and Fiscal Records, Miscellaneous Records, Fiduciary Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1816-1848
  Land Records, County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Court Records, Fiduciary Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Miscellaneous Records, School Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1820-1826
  Miscellaneous Records, Court Records, Fiduciary Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1822-1848
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Tax and Fiscal, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1823-1830
  Tax and Fiscal Records, County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Miscellaneous Records, School Records, Fiduciary Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1827-1914
  Tax and Fiscal Records, School Records, Election Records, Miscellaneous Records, Fiduciary Records, Road and Bridge Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1827-1843
  Fiduciary Records, Court Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, School Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths.
- Records, circa 1831-1856
  School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Election Records, Miscellaneous Records, Fiduciary Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1832-1843
  Tax and Fiscal Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Court Records, County Administrative Records: Sheriff's Records, Miscellaneous Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, School Records, Election Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1837-1852
  Miscellaneous Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Election Records, School Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1840-1858
  Fiduciary Records, Court Records, School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths.
- Records, circa 1840-1850
  Court Records, Fiduciary Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, School Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1844-1857
  County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, School Records, Election Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Miscellaneous Records, Court Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1850-1857
  Tax and Fiscal Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records, Miscellaneous Records, School Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1852-1874
  Miscellaneous Records, Land Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Road and Bridge Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1850-1879
  Road and Bridge Records, Fiduciary Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Election Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1850-1856
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Fiduciary Records, Court Records, School Records--includes the Lectures of Professor John B. Minor.
- Records, circa 1870-1879
  Court Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Fiduciary Records.
- Records, circa 1870-1895
  Court Records, Election Records, Miscellaneous Records, Fiduciary Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Land Records:Deeds, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1873-1882
  Election Records, Court Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records, Road and Bridge Records, Land Records:Deeds, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Fiduciary Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1875-1884
  Court Records, Road and Bridge Records, Election Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Fiduciary Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1879-1887
  Road and Bridge Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, County Administrative Records: Treasurer's Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, School Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1880-1918
  Court Records and Miscellaneous Records.
- Records, circa 1880-1885
  Road and Bridge Records, School Records--includes records of the Miller Manual Labor School, Tax and Fiscal Records, Fiduciary Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Miscellaneous Records, Court Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1882-1886
  Road and Bridge Records, Fiduciary Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Tax and Fiscal Records, School Records, Court Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1883-1893
  Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships, Road and Bridge Records, Court Records, Miscellaneous Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, School Records, County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1885-1916
  Tax and Fiscal Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Road and Bridge Records, Fiduciary Records, Court Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1886-1892
  Miscellaneous Records, Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Court Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records, Organization Records--includes records of the Northwestern Masonic Aid Association. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1886-1893
  Election Records, Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships, Court Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Road and Bridge Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1890-1917
  Court Records, Miscellaneous Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Road and Bridge Records, Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1893-1897
  Court Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Road and Bridge Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1892-1909
  Court Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Road and Bridge Records, Election Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records. UNPROCESSED
- Records, circa 1892-1904
  Court Records, Miscellaneous Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Tax and Fiscal Records, Land Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1900-1930
  Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships, Land Records, Miscellaneous Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, School Records, Court Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1902-1930
  Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Miscellaneous Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records, Court Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1913-1936
  Tax and Fiscal Records, Court Records, Road and Bridge Records, Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1912-1941
  School Records and Election Records.
- Records, undated
  Tax and Fiscal Records, Justice of the Peace Records, School Records, Road and Bridge Records, dates undetermined.
- Records, circa 1880-1938
  Land Records, Road and Bridge Records, Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships, Tax and Fiscal Records. Oversized. Includes newspaper clippings.
- Records, 1858-1870
  CIVIL WAR ERA Box 5: Justice of the Peace Records: Constable's Records, 1858; Business Records: Contracts and Agreements, 1858-1866; Miscellaneous Records: Estray Papers, 1858-1968; Business Records: Fire Co. Papers, 1866; Health and Medical Records, 1863-1870; Military and Pension Records: Impressment Papers, 1864; Court Records: Jailer's Records, 1858-1870; Health and Medical: Lunacy Papers, 1858, 1868; Miscellaneous Papers, 1867; County Administrative Records: Overseers of the Poor, 1858-1871; Land Records: Petition for Exemption from Fence Law, 1866-1877.
- Records, 1789-1904, undated
  Bonds/Oaths/Commissions: Commission of John M. White judge of 8th Judicial Circuit (1904); Certification of Mijacah Woods as Justice of the Peace (n.d.); Court Records: General District Court Docket, (1789); Court Records: Personal Documentation: certificate of character for Richard [Snow?] (1845); Court Records: Personal Documentation: Declarations of intent (1822-1852); Tax and Fiscal Records: Schedule of John Jordan's property (n.d.)
- Records, circa 1823-1916
  Court Records: Correspondence re: George S. Shackelford, attorney at law, 1880-1881; Letters related to incarceration of Daniel Johnson, 1907; Gilmer family genealogical charts; Organization Records: Catalogue of the Ellerslie Yearlings - Property of Arthur B. Hancock, 1916; All God's Children - pamphlet published by Albemarle Child Welfare Association, no date; Court Records: Copy of answer - Fluvanna County Chancery Cause, James Johnson vs. Nicholas Johnson, 1823; Judgments: Debt account - Colonel T. J. Randolph to William Jeffries, 1874; Deposition - unidentified Judgemnt suit; Court Records: Grand Jury Presentment, no date.
- Records, 1790-1857
  Fiduciary Records (estate), 1790-1807; County Adminstrative Records: Board of Supervisor Records: Road and Bridge Records, 1855, 1857; Land Records: 1834, 1845, 1855; Court Records: Judgments: Johnson vs. Admr of Hunter, 1816.